This task is again a CodeWorld task which
is based on another task we had before.
And that one is the rising sun task which
we're going to advance on with this task.
Here again we have a preview of what we shall
do and also an animation which demonstrates what
we shall not do and then another one where
we can see what advancements are possible.
So first of all - this is what we want
to do: We want to have the sun rising;
and when the sun is sunken, then we want to
have the moon rising and so on and so forth.
And this is not what we want to do - so the moon
shall not rotate during the rising and setting.
And this is an advancement that we
can do. When this sun is rising we
have just the sky, and when the moon is
rising we have additionally some stars.
Okay, so first of all let's go back to our task.
This time is a bit different, so we have
blanks in here instead of 'undefined's
and we can replace the parts of the program here.
So first of all let's run the code here.
So nothing is happening
because we have these blanks
in here and the scene defines - or -
is defined as grass and sun or moon.
Yeah, okay - let's stop this animation
here first of all and then I insert
code which we had in the previous task
- which is definitions of the scene.
This time, yeah, the scene looks different, so
we have already a definition for the scene given.
And this one is one of the older tasks and
I've included another version of it as well.
And yeah. And we have the grass. So,
let's take the grass as we had it before.
So I remove the given part of grass and
replace it with the old one. And yeah.
And then we change the part for sun or moon.
So, we have sun or moon given here and
let's just place the old part of the scene,
but without the grass into the sun or moon part.
So, well, let's see what's happening here.
So, now it's basically what we had in the old
task and if I run this stuff we shall see a
sun which is rising and then setting again
and standing still there at a certain point.
Now, what was different in the previous
task: we had the start and end point.
So, we don't need this one anymore; so we can
remove the start and end point first of all.
So, let's just say we have the position given
by t here and we remove this part here.
So, now.
Now we, yeah, if we run this one here,
we have a rising sun and the setting sun, and
then it continues to go beneath our horizon.
That's not what we want to do. But, yeah, we
want it to be different for - so we want to
have the sun rising and then the moon rising,
so we have two parts we want to insert here.
And how can we decide whether we want
to have the sun rising or the moon?
Well, we have the t parameter again, and we know
that it is a half circle; we want to have the sun
available and the half circle we want to have
the moon available as both are going to be
rotating for a certain amount of time
- and this shall be a half circle.
And so, we, as we do the moving by using
this t parameter here directly - this t
parameter - we can say that this is exactly
the point where t gets to the value of pi.
So, if we change that then we are
- well, say that the rotation should go to the
- yeah - to the time point where the - value
is less than pi, then we can say - so t is less
than pi, then we want to have the sun moving.
So, and I'm using a guard here and we can
use another guard which says otherwise
we want to move the moon. So,
translated x and y - and the - moon.
So, this is a rather naive
implementation. And? Would it work now?
Well, what's happening?
We are moving the sun and then we
are moving the moon; well, the moon
is at the wrong position - and
then it continues to run so.
There are two points wrong.
First of all, the moon is going
below the grass, which is not what we
want, and then the moon continues to move.
So, let's first of all fix the
moon going below the grass level.
We can introduce a function move
here for the translated part.
Because we have it defined in both parts here;
we have 'translated' for sun and for moon
and we want to have the
same moving for both parts.
So we can introduce a new function
called move, and this one shall move
our objects - which is p
So it's some picture p we want to move.
So this is just a simple refactoring.
We do move of sun and move of moon.
And move is of type picture to picture.
So we can now move this one, and we need another
parameter which is t, which is our time for moving.
So, now we can have the same
implementation as before.
Nothing has changed; if we run the
program, we get the same result.
But now we can say that we want to move the moon
by simply saying we move the moon
when we have the time point minus pi.
So that should lead to moving
the moon after the sun, starting from
here again. Which is happening here.
But still, the moon continues to
move - that's not what we want.
So? How can we fix this part?
Well, I said here we use the time point t
when it's lower than pi for moving the sun.
What we actually want is we have used our
trigonometric functions here already sine of t.
And if we use this one, we can say:
Well, actually we want to move the sun when we have
a time point where the sine of t is above zero.
So, we can say
we want to have all the time points where sine
of t is greater than zero for moving the sun.
So now, we move with the first time point of the,
of the rotation; we move the sun and, with the,
where the sine is less than
zero, we move the moon.
And now the animation continues, and we have
sun rising, moon rising, sun rising,
moon rising, and so on and so forth.
Yeah, there is another version of
doing the same stuff, which is
based on the other implementation
we had within last week.
There we had something like this here.
I think, oh this one, this part here was a negate,
so actually we wrote it like this - negate.
And let me just choose this scene in
order to demonstrate the other part.
- so this is exactly the same
movement as before without
changing the parts of the
rotation and adding the moon. So.
And what we have to do is roughly the same.
We, first of all, remove the start
and end points and just use t.
So I remove this min and
max here and we use just t.
And we remove the start and endpoint.
So, and if we do this now, our sun
should continue to rotate the whole time.
Okay, and I stop this one again.
Now we can simply have the same guards here, so
we can introduce the same guards as below here.
So we say when this sine of
t is greater than 0, then we
use -
Oh,
I just figured out that I shouldn't have
changed the scene - in fact, I should have
changed the sunOrMoon function in
order to have the same behavior.
So let me rename this one to sun or moon
and
I keep the scene function here.
And this is sunOrMoon2 - okay.
I'm sorry for the confusion.
So, now we have the guard again here, and
this is actually not complete yet, because -
oh, we have a non-exhaustive
pattern-match in function sunOrMoon.
This is because we have
no case for the otherwise.
So it shall happen otherwise, and let's
just make this one blank for the moment.
So!
And, yeah, we can apply the
same part as before - we -
or the same trick.
We can define a move here which
is again used for sun and moon.
And thus, we can because of if here -
well let me just introduce the moon here.
If we introduce the moon here,
we don't see anything because
the moon is hidden behind the grass.
So we need to translate it and move
it as well, as we did with the sun.
So we introduce a new function move here
again as we did in the other case as well.
And we take the rotated part here again
for moving. So I take this part here
and say move t shall be
the moving of the sun.
And then we have the moving of the moon again.
Yeah. Here's a missing bracket! So this one.
And of course, I've missed
the picture we want to move.
So this is exactly as we want to
have it for moving sun and moon!
And again the moon is moving below the
grass; this is because we have forgotten to
say that we want to change the
- the angle for the movement.
So, we want minus pi for the angles
because we just want to have the
rising and setting part above the grass.
And still, when we do this, we
see that the moon is rotating.
And this is not what we want!
We want the moon to move
just as smoothly as the sun.
We didn't have this issue in the other
case because we were translating using
cosine and sine functions.
In this case, we have to fix this part.
And we can fix this part by
rotating the moon. So, and we can rotate the moon
just by using t again.
So.
If we just were using something like this,
we can - because yeah, well -
now we rotate by t and we rotate
the complete animation by using negate, and now
we should see that the moon is not moving again.
Because - yeah - they are rotated in other parts.
However, we have introduced another error.
The moon is pointing in the other direction.
How can we fix this?
Well, this happened because - when we look here -
we have t set to minus pi and because
of t minus pi in this case and
just t in that case we have
rotated our moon by 180 degrees.
We can fix this part by introducing
the rotation in our move function.
So, when we put the rotation in here
then we use this t here, which is t minus pi
in this case, or let's, to make it more clear:
I just say t' here to
signify this is another t.
So we use here another t in
order to rotate the moon.
And when we do this one, then we get
our animation with the moon
in the correct direction.
Okay. Now we can think about adding
some more stuff there. We had stars
in the one animation. I just want
to show something like this here.
So we can think about how to create a star.
And for simplicity of showing the stars
well, I just added to the scene here
and we define now a new function or no
a new variable star, which is a picture.
So it's just one star as a picture.
And - well, we have a choice of options in order
to create those parts; I choose a polygon here!
And I think we can, well, we can draw a star
by giving the points of all the
parts that belong to the star.
I don't want to give all the parts;
that's why I draw a part of this star.
And I used the solidPolygon function which
is defined in the API. So we can ...
solidPolygon - which gets a series
of points and draws a picture.
So, solidPolygon, and I draw a bigger star,
just because I can think about the values more
easily. So, we start at
point (1, 0) and then we go
to (0.25, 0.25) and move up to (1, 0) right and
now up to (0, 1) and then we add point (0, 0).
And if you could follow me - we will now get
a polygon - which draws a part of a star.
So we're drawing here just one part of
the star and I want to have this star
all filled by having the other parts as well.
And, yeah, I could add more points
in order to draw the complete star.
But I choose another way here - which is
- using another function of CodeWorld.
There is the 'reflected' function and this
reflects across a line through the
origin at this angle in radians.
So we can use a part of an object
and reflect it through the origin.
Okay, and I demonstrate this part by
applying this function to solid angle.
So we use 'reflected', and in this case, I
reflect it to the angle of 180
degrees, which is in radians pi.
And if I do this, then we get
the star part below here - okay?
But I do not want to have the reflection -
I want to have the original part as well.
So I want to have this part combined with
this part.
Like, like this here, okay?
But I do not want to
duplicate the code, thus I introduce a function
which does this and I call this function 'mirrored'.
And mirrored has two parameters; it has the angle
and the picture as values it gets, and it returns
a picture again.
So we have an angle and a picture and we
return the reflected picture by
angle and the picture itself.
So. And if we use mirrored instead of reflected.
Well - we get half of a star.
And we can apply the same trick once
more in order to get the full star by
reflecting it across the y-axis.
And how can we reflect across the y-axis?
Well, we mirror it by pi or ...
so this is the horizontal reflection, but we can
rotate it by pi and a half, which is 90 degrees
or mirror it at this axis and
then we get a complete star.
And now we can scale this one.
I use the 'dilated' function in
order to make it a bit smaller. And
so let's say one third of the original size.
So, now we have a little star.
And we can, if we want, we can colorize
the whole picture by applying colored.
Yeah, and now the line is
getting long already, so I
indent the code a bit in order
to make it more readable. So!
Now we have all the parameters for the star.
And have a little star here.
Okay. And we can add the star to the night sky.
Well, we can do this by giving certain parameters
to move the star to a certain part of the sky.
Yeah, so let's create a value of
stars which shall again be a picture.
And first of all, let's say
stars are translated by,
yeah, a value of x and y -
let's just say five and eight.
And then the star - so and now - the star is here
and so now we can move one star to that position
well, okay, we have one star
here but we want to have more.
Luckily for this case, we
have the function 'pictures'
which
takes a list of pictures and returns a picture.
And we already know about list comprehension.
So we can use list comprehension
in order to create a set of stars.
So we can say we want to have pictures
which are translated by x and y.
And we give a list of x and y's.
And the star, all stars,
shall be part of this list.
So, now we can add some values
where we want to position the stars,
and this can be any values you like.
I just take values that are above the x-axis.
And then I choose some values on the
left-hand side and so we have negative x
and some that are on the right
hand side with positive x.
So - this one was a mistake.
So I choose y values that are above zero!
And then they should fill the sky.
And well, we can just add some
stars and then we have a starry sky.
Sure, of course, we just want
to have these stars at night!
So we add them in our 'sunOrMoon' function and
say we have stars only when the moon is there.
So we say stars & move .. moon and then we have
the moon only when - when the - or
the stars only when it is night. So!
Okay. And instead of choosing the positions
for the stars by - yeah - by giving values
you can, of course, use different variations
of the list comprehension features in order to
generate a set of x and y coordinates in
order to distribute stars across the sky.
And maybe to do some fancy stuff like
have these stars aligned like within
the European Union flag or something like
this; using rotation and so on and so forth.
But I won't demonstrate this
here, so I will stop right here.
And yeah, I just give the basics for this task.